Welcome to the lighter side of the
spectrum.
The podcast that celebrates the multiple
hats we wear and the juggling acts we
perform in life. Whether you're parenting
kids and teens on the autism spectrum,
navigating the ever-evolving healthcare
industry, or building a more inclusive and
impactful world, this is your space to
find connection, inspiration, and growth.
Together, we'll share stories, tackle
challenges, and explore how innovation and
inclusion create better outcomes for
everyone. Because no matter the spectrum,
there's always a lighter side. Now here's
your host.
David Coffer. Hello again, everybody. This
is David Coffer. Welcome back to the
lighter side of the spectrum, where we
explore the people, ideas, and stone. Hi.
How
are you? Good. Happy. Okay, no good. And
conversations that help us better
understand autism, communication, and what
it really means to support human
potential.
You know, one of the things I've certainly
learned over the last few years is that
so many of the assumptions that we make
about people turn out to be wrong. We've
learned that what looks like a lack of
understanding may actually be a motor
planning challenge. We've also learned
that what looks like a behavioral issue
may
be sensory overload. What appears to be an
inability to communicate may simply be a
person who hasn't been given the right way
to communicate.
Today's conversation is going to ask us to
consider another assumption. What if
vision isn't just about seeing clearly?
You know, most of us think of vision as
reading, the eye chart at your doctor's
office, trying to see if you have 2020
vision. You know, if you're good, you're
good to go. But what if your eyes are
healthy yet your brain isn't using them
together in the way it's meant to be?
What if the issue isn't how well you see,
but how you see? And that's the
fascinating world we're gonna step into
today. And my guest today is Denise Allen,
host of Healing Our Sight Podcast, and a
passionate advocate for helping people
better understand binocular vision and the
remarkable adaptability of the human
brain.
Denise spent most of her life with
Strabomide Strabimus. I knew I was gonna
screw it
up. Well help me, Denise. Strabismus. I
even practiced it. And without
stereoscopic
or 3D vision, like many people, she
assumed that was simply the way her brain
worked. But as an adult, she discovered
that our visual system may be far more
adaptable than many of us realize.
business.
And that journey led her into the worlds
of vision therapy, neuroplasty,
developmental optometry, and neuroscience.
Along the way, she's had conversations
with leading experts while helping
parents, patients, and professionals
better
understand conditions and related to
vision-related challenges. So this isn't
about
Autism specifically, but we certainly see
it within autism. And I think it's really
gonna be a fascinating conversation
because vision, sensory processing, motor
planning, communication, they're all parts
of an incredibly complex system. So
Denise, with all that being said, thanks
for joining me today. I'm really looking
forward to this conversation.
Thanks for having me.
Yeah. So why don't you tell us a little
bit about your experience? What tell us
about what is it like to grow up with this
condition?
Well, you know, I didn't know anything
different. So I thought I was pretty
normal.
But I did have struggles with
coordination, being very clumsy, not very
good at
catching or th you know, balls or
anything, any moving object coming at me
was
difficult to gauge where it was and catch
it. So I was really bad at ball games. So
I was usually chosen last, you know, that
kind of thing.
Right.
that posed a problem, of course. my knees
were always scraped up, you know. I fell
down. I just thought I was a clumsy kid,
you know.
Yeah so you just thought you were clumsy,
I mean right? Like you hear about that.
So my mom put me in dance class. That was
supposed to help. Didn't love it that
much. No, it did it did help. And then I
actually did gymnastics in junior high,
which I shouldn't have probably been able
to do very well. I was too tall for it.
Wow. But yeah, that that's challenging.
It's it doesn't stop someone from doing
something that they want to do. My
brother, who had the same condition, only
his
No.
showed up when he was a baby. he became a
basketball player. He played college
basketball, which also shouldn't really be
very easy. But he was passionate about
basketball. Wow. So he overcame that. So I
think we don't have to discount anything,
right? But the thing that I found is that
it can be
Stone's very excited today. So again, he's
making lots of appearances. He's getting
ready to head out with his brother. That's
amazing though. I mean, that he was able
to play basketball. Because again, why do
you I mean we'll back up a little bit and
maybe kind of talk about Strabismus. Is
that I get better that okay. what is it,
you
know, and in
Yeah.
How is it defined and how does it impact
people?
Yeah, so strabismus is when the eyes don't
focus together. And the easy explanation
is just that they're fighting with each
other all the time. And i in order to
compensate for that, one of the eyes will
shut off. And when you look at someone,
often that eye is pointing in the another
direction. Okay. Because it's getting out
of the way of the other eye that's the
strong eye. So you'll see.
kids with an eye turn, right? Crossed
eyes, w however you want to term it,
right? It
can be turning in or it can be turning
out. people will call it a lazy eye.
Yeah, you hear you hear about that. Okay,
so that's kind of
And so it it's like five percent of the
population that have an actual strabismus
like this. The normal population. If
you're looking at the autistic spectrum,
then
it's to totally different. And that's just
strabismus. That's not other vision
problems like inability to track or other
focusing types of issues like that. You
know, so my
Mine is kind of a subset, but it's a much
bigger problem than that.
Is this something that we're just like so
many other things, we're just learning
more about? I mean, is there just is it
one that's we're just getting more
awareness? Because growing up, I mean,
what was like you said, you were just kind
of
considered maybe a little clumsy or you
went in for traditional eye exams, right?
Like, you know, was it just what did the
eye doctors see or say, you know, and what
did it take for you to finally figure it
out?
Yeah, that is a great question. And I and
I think that it's always been a problem. I
just feel like the fact that we can do
something about it hasn't been very
obvious.
So when I my brother, it was obvious at
birth. He went into the doctor, they did
surgery on his eyes because it was
pointing way in, you know.
So it was so obvious that like they're
like, Okay, we gotta fix this. I mean
Exactly. Yeah. And the traditional
solution f when you have this kind of an
eye turn
is the ophthalmologist will say, Well,
we're gonna do surgery. They'll do two or
three surgeries. It often it takes more
than one. My brother had three surgeries.
Yeah, two when he was a baby and one when
he was like seven to kind of tune it up.
So it's kind of a lot of surgery for a
young child. It doesn't teach the eyes how
to
work together though, to have surgery.
Oh wow.
So even though my brother's eyes were
fairly straight, he didn't learn how to
see
depth. My problem didn't surface until I
was almost three. So it's a different type
of strabismus. There's infantile like my
brother, and then there's c a compensatory
type of strabismus. And it usually means
that you have either far sighted or
nearsightedness and your eyes are not
working together and they're compensating.
And
they put glasses on the child like they
did me.
And the eyes look pretty straight and the
doctor says, Okay, you're good to go.
Just because just because your eyes are
straight. Exactly.
Exactly. And a I remember a as a child
going in for my yearly exam and I was
about
ten and they did this test where you look
in the big machine and on one side there's
a note and on the other side there's the
five lines for the music staff. And they
said, Can you tell us what line or space
that note's on?
And I said, Well, I see the notes over
here and I see the lines over here. Do you
want me to guess? And I had been guessing
until then. Something just clicked and I
thought and I was and I was annoyed
because we I'd had a traumatic event on
the way
to the office. And so I think I was pr
probably a little more sassy than usual,
you
know?
Really?
Yeah. A little edgy. A little edgy ten
year old.
And I just said, Do you want me to guess?
Because I can't I see 'em on, you know,
with each eye. And I'd had never been able
to see through binoculars or, you know,
the little kaleidoscope thing. The Yeah. I
could never do those. and they just said,
Oh, you can't do that. We won't do that
anymore.
Oh yeah. Those were fun. Yeah.
That was their answer? Yeah. Oh great.
That's helpful. Yeah.
And you know, vision therapy has been
around that long but nobody knew about it.
I
didn't know about it until I went f
looking for answers as a you know, forty
something year old because my eyes were
bothering me more at that point.
Well, I think there's still a real lack of
understanding about vision therapy. yeah,
it was something I'd heard about again in
our journey with autism ourselves. That's
just one of many avenues that you explore
when you're dealing with communication.
And I remember hearing about we have a
place I'm in the Seattle area, and you
know,
checking out, but that was all new, just
the whole idea of doing vision therapy,
because again, it's so
Absolutely.
yeah, you just think about just you just
get eye exams and you get classes. You
don't think about this as something
another area, although it makes perfect
sense
once you start looking at it a little more
closely.
Right. Yeah. And I didn't start looking
until my eye turn started to become really
bad in my forties. I started to get
presbyopia like a lot of us do at that
age, you
know. Can't see till you're, you know,
have your hand clear out here. And so my
eye
turn just got worse and I looked at
natural vision improvement things and I
started
searching online and I just by accident
Wow.
Not by accident, right. Came across vision
therapy, found out there was a doctor
just down the street from me. And there
were only two in the whole state of Utah
at
that point. And went in and had an exam
and f figured out that there was something
we could do.
Wow. Well that's I'm glad that you found
that. What was it like then? I mean, what
and how tell me about that experience as
you after you went through started going
through the therapy, did you experience
like true depth perception for the first
time or you know, things like that?
Well, it wasn't quite that easy. Yeah. No.
it was about two thousand thirteen. I
started vision therapy, did a lot of
sessions of therapy, and I just wasn't
getting
any solu any resolution at all. I wasn't
getting any progress. And my doctor said,
you know, you can look at surgery, that
could be
It wasn't like
What you might want to do in addition, and
I didn't want to do surgery, so I stopped
vision therapy, took my daughter in, found
out that she was mini me and that she
Okay. It's really genetic, it sounds like
Well, I knew
Yeah. It's hard to say. It's yeah, it's
hard to say. But I mean I have six
children.
My youngest daughter was just like me. I
knew she was like me because she had an
eye
turn when she was three, like I did. And I
had taken her to the doctor and they put
her in glasses. It was just, you know, the
same process. And she was fine. She did
fine in school. She didn't seem to
struggle that much in other things. She
didn't
seem to be s super clumsy.
I had done other things with her when she
was very young, like music and movement. I
taught music and movement classes. And so
there were things that maybe compensated
better. I don't know. And I didn't see her
doing poorly in school or having any
struggles. And I had this passion for
sharing the whole thing, you know, because
I
knew it could help. I hadn't helped me
yet, but I knew it could.
And so I was reading this book called W if
when your ch Sorry When Your Child
Struggles by David Cook. And it had a
checklist in it of things to ask the
child.
And I was thinking about it in
relationship to c children that I was
experiencing at
school when I was substitute teaching. But
I practice I decided to practice the
questions on my daughter. And so I said I
said to her, Do the words ever do this
when you're reading?
And you know, the split apart. And she
said yes. And I thought, Oh, that's not
good.
I had no idea that she was seeing double
when she
And how old was she at this point? Remind
me. Okay, so about okay. Yeah.
She was nine. Okay. Yeah. So very m
starting to be very aware of that. And
potentially have problems later on, you
know, because reading just the words just
keep getting smaller, right? And more
difficult. so I said, Well do you ever
close
an eye when you're reading? That was also
on the checklist. And she said, Oh yeah,
ev all the time when I'm reading in bed, I
s I s I lay with my eye
Yeah.
on the pillow so that I'm reading just
with the one eye and she said and then I
turn
over when I turn the page and do it with
the other eye.
That was helping avoid double vision,
right? And I had
She kind of s figured it out. Like she had
her own solution. I mean to exactly cope
with it was a co it was a coping
mechanism, basically.
Exactly. Yes. And I don't know if she did
any of that at school. Sometimes children
will, you know, they'll sit with their
hand up like this, you know, cover an eye.
And just make other compensator
compensatory items that will help them to
not have
that problem. So she was doing all of
those things. I had no idea. And I thought
I
was a pretty aware mom, you know, she was
child number six.
You know, it I kind of was beating myself
up a little bit about it, you know. So I
took her into my vision therapy doctor and
he got her in vision therapy. It took
about nine months of therapy for her and
she was able to gain three D.
So it was a pretty easy process. It is
something for a lot of people that you
kinda
have to keep doing a little bit of to keep
the skill.
Kinda like exercise in a way.
A little bit, yeah. So I think she might
have lost a little ground. We've talked
about that over the years. She's been on
my podcast too and told her story. So it
she recognizes that there might be some
things she could do to kind of strengthen
her ability still. in the meantime my
daughter
Yeah.
It does. Yeah, it does. And for some
people it takes way longer, you know? And
there
are cases that take less time. But I think
nine months is a fairly standard or
comfortable amount of time that it will
take for people if they're if for kids,
you
know, kids are much more malle malleable
than adults are. So oh
Yeah, absolutely.
I went back in at the end of that process.
My doctor had done some training in and
some other kinds of therapy. I went in, I
tried those, and still wasn't getting the
results I wanted. At this point, I'm like
80 sessions in division therapy. And once
again, he said, You probably need to look
at the surgery. So
He referred me to a doctor that he's
worked with. I went in, I had the
strabismus
surgery. Okay. So that your eyes are lined
up instead of crossed.
Wow. I mean that's a big step. I could see
why you know, you would want to avoid it
if at all possible. I think anytime for
most of us, right, you talk about our eyes
or eye surgery is just it's different. It
hits different than just saying, Oh, you
know, you we gotta do some elbow surgery,
for example, or something like that.
Well, I mean when you're cutting a muscle,
I j I think it's y you tend to hesitate
before you're
It's your eyes. It's your eyes. All right.
Like that's very personal to all of us.
So but it sounds like it was it sounds
like obviously it was a success.
Yeah, it was amazing. I had a really easy
time with the surgery. I took like one
pain med. I decided the pain meds weren't
really helping me. I not doing good things
to my body. Okay not doing that. And so
I'm really into natural remedies. So I
took
this homeopathic remedy called Arnica. Oh,
okay. Instead of any of the other drugs
they had given me and I went back for my
check up a m a week later and my eye
doctor said, I can't believe how fast
you've
recovered from this surgery. Great, thank
you. and I r that week I also went back
into vision therapy. And they don't
necessarily recommend that you do that.
You
know, a lot of times doctors will say, Oh,
you should recover first or whatever. I
mean I was recovered, but not everybody
will go back in that quickly. And
Wow.
As soon as I went back in, I could do
everything that I hadn't been able to be
for.
Wow. That must have been amazing.
It was. Yeah. And I gained r you know,
pretty good depth perception, especially
close up. My depth perceptions in normal
range. Further out, it's not quite as
good.
So I'm still working on that.
And I'm just curious, do you have twenty
vision as well now? Or do you
there's no relationship between the way
that the eyes focus together and the
acuity
piece. Yeah. We think that vision is just
all about seeing 2020. And it's not at
all. So vision therapy doesn't fix that
piece. Okay. I still need glasses. Okay.
So
I mean I wear contacts. But yeah, that
piece doesn't get fixed by therapy.
Right.
So the vision.
like that. And there are other things that
we can do to improve the acuity piece,
but that's not typically done in a regular
doctor's office. You know, that kind of
goes into the realm of natural vision
improvement.
Okay. But that's remarkable that you
recover that quickly. Do you attribute it
to
the homeopathic approach that you took or
just your you know, were there other steps
that you took that maybe helped accelerate
it?
I think that that's what I've typically
attributed it to, but I also am really
healthy and mindset also plays into it.
The fact that I had never had a surgery
before made it easier. You know, people
who've had other strabismus surgeries,
there's scar tissue that's gonna get in
the way and it makes it a harder process.
No, that makes a lot of sense. You know,
early w you were talking about how it
affects what you know, roughly five
percent of the general population, but the
pi
the percentage is a lot higher when you're
talking about the neurodiverse or the aut
you know, autistic population. Do you have
any estimates of how it is?
I thought you might ask me that. So I
pulled out this book that I like. It's
called
I can you see it?
Yeah, I guess yeah.
The Hidden Link Between Vision and
Learning by Wendy Rosen. She's one of my
podcast
guests. And I knew she had told me this
and that I had read it. And so I looked it
up. And it says, according to her, that
about 25% of children in the in the United
States struggle with learning problems.
And then 25% of children also have a
vision
problem that impedes learning. So let's
see, maybe there's a connection there,
right?
And according to the National Center for
Health Statistics, 20 to 25% of children
enter school with significant vision
problems. So, and that's, I mean, that's
not
just strubismus, that's other vision
issues, right? the greatest difficulty
among
learning disabled children is with
reading, which is affecting 75% of that
population. And 80% of these children
struggle with one or more visual skills.
Wow.
So that's a huge number.
That is a huge number. And I as you're
talking about it, I'm thinking, you know,
as
it relates to the autistic and the non
speaking community, is that how
frustrating
that must be. So, you know, because there
are a lot of non speakers who have gained
communication through the letter border
typing or you know other methodologies.
That that's when it finally comes out that
they have vision issues. It could be
double vision or you know, so similar
types of issues. Of course they had no way
to
share that before. Right? So they're like
you said, they're trying to they're trying
to cope they're trying to cope with vision
issues without having the way to share
that, to communicate, like, hey, I'm I
can't see in three D or I can't, you know,
I'm seeing double of every you know, these
words are all of that.
Yeah. Well and I mean everyone thinks that
this is just the way you see. They have
no idea that someone else sees differently
than they do.
Right, Like to your point, like growing
up, right, growing up, you're like, oh
it's
just the this is just the way it is.
Yeah, my daughter had no idea that anyone
saw any differently than she did either,
you know.
And she didn't think it was and she didn't
think it was I wanna say weird, you know,
but different. She didn't think anything
about reading the way that she wrote read,
for example. Like that was just the way it
was. I you just, you know, cover up one
eye and roll over and do the other eye.
And that's just the yeah, that's just what
you do. Yep. So what role does
neuroplasticity play in vision? I mean,
what you
know, when it comes to this, like you
said, it's not just twenty you know,
looking
twenty Are there
Hello.
Exactly.
Are the ther is vision therapy, does that
deal with issues with the brain in terms
of training the brain as well?
That's exactly what it's doing. Yeah.
Okay. We're training the brain to see
correctly. Cause the eyes themselves are
just an organ, right? They the muscles are
not gonna do anything you don't tell 'em
to do. So if the brain isn't telling the
eyes what to do, you're not gonna see
properly.
Regardless, you know, it real vision
really is just in the brain and we don't
think
of it that way. We think it's what our
eyes are seeing, you know. But I mean our
arms aren't gonna move if our brain
doesn't tell it to. So why do we think our
eyes
know what to do if our brain doesn't tell
'em what to do?
Why do we think that, Denise? That's a
good question. I mean th that 'cause it's
true. That's a absolutely the perception.
You don't think of it as a muscle, you
don't think of it as something that your
brain has to control. I guess unless
you're
really in a situation when you that kind
of focus is required.
Anything from like looking through a
microscope or binoculars or you know,
whatever
where you're like, Oh, you know, you're
actually focused on the task at hand, I
guess. You just take it for granted? I
mean
We all take it for granted all the time.
And Yeah.
Do you Yeah. Go ahead. Kind of like
walking. Again, you do you take advan you
take
it for granted if you're able to walk.
Right. If you've gone through that
progression, you know, that's all you
know. You learn to crawl, you learn to
walk.
You want to go from point A to point B,
you walk there. You don't think about your
brains telling your legs to move. I guess
it's the same for vision.
Exactly.
And if our eye muscles aren't working
properly, it's no different than any other
muscle in our body, you know, and we do
exercise to strengthen those muscles or to
relax those muscles, right? And in the
case of our eyes, we really need to relax
the
muscles in order for them to see properly.
And we never think of it that way either,
you know.
No, not at all. I mean you're starting to
see some awareness in terms of eyes. I'm
thinking about like with eye fatigue now
with all the screen time, you know, things
kind of related to that. Hey, you need to
give your eyes a break. You know, you
don't want to be staring at a screen for
hours on end and all that. But I still
feel
like it's fairly shallow in terms of the
approach that we take.
I agree. Absolutely. Yep.
yeah, I was thinking also with especially
with kids and screen time and you know,
this all overlaps, but could some you
know, could these problems sometimes l
look
like ADHD or learning disabilities or
sensory issues?
Absolutely. Yeah. And the fact that we see
it in this population should point that
out a little bit. You know, if the same
kids that are struggling are the ones who
have a vision problem, then w you know,
which came first? And what's the best way
to
deal with it, right? And you know, I have
another favorite book that I wanted to
share.
Yeah, I'm pleased.
There's well, there's a couple that were
written by Robin and Gillian Benoit. One
of
them's called Jillian's Story. And then I
have this one as Dear Jillian. And they
talk in this book about well, in the first
one, she tells Jillian's story. And
Jillian had amblyopia. she had passed
every eye exam. And the way she passed it,
and
I don't know if you know what amblyopia is
or if you're
I do not
Okay. Well s it's a type of strabismus.
Amblyopia you have lower acuity in one
eye.
So if you can't see very well out of one
eye, you're just gonna use the other eye.
And that eye just kind of shuts off. And
it sometimes if that happens for a long
period of time, the person really goes
blind in that eye. And it just kinda
becomes
they treat it as a permanent kind of
problem. I don't agree that any of that's
permanent, but
There's different perceptions on that.
Anyway, Jillian had pretty significant
amblyopia, but she'd passed every test
when they've done the eye exam at the
school
because she thought it was like a
memorization test. And so she would listen
to the
kids in front of her and she wanted to get
the treat, right? And so she would just
rattle off whatever they said, even though
she couldn't see it at all.
Wow. That's I mean it's ingenious, but
again not helpful in term
Exactly. Yeah. And so when she finally got
into vision therapy, then, you know, she
was able to overcome that and gain 3D
vision and then tell her story, you know.
And
then all these people started writing to
her saying, Hey, let me tell you my story.
And that's what went into the second book,
right? And she did talk to someone that
was autistic. Their family. Right.
Oh interesting.
And that's why I wanted to share this
because I think it this is a really great
story about it. he this child was only two
when they figured out that he well he was
diagnosed as autistic, but then they
figured out that he also had an eye issue
that
could be helped with vision therapy. So
they took him to vision therapy and he was
able to progress so much that he
graduated from the autistic program that
he was in with the school system. They
said
he doesn't qualify as being autistic
anymore. So I think that that's just kind
of
points to the fact that there's so much
more going on.
Interesting. Yeah.
So much more going on. Absolutely.
And we c we can we can look at the
symptoms and say, well, it's gotta be
this, but
that may not be the case, you know. And so
there's a lot of misdiagnosis of ADHD and
dyslexia and all of those learning issues
that we really should check the vision to
see if that's what's causing the problem,
or if it can help the problem. It's all
working together.
Right, for sure.
And it seems that there is not a big
emphasis on vision screening, really. I
mean it
kind of it's almost like kind of a last
resort. And do you think again, is that
lack
of awareness, Denise, or is it just
resources? I mean what how what would you
attribute or would you
There's so much that goes into that's such
a loaded question. I had I had to remove
myself from the school system because it
was such a hot topic for me personally.
Because I wanted to go in there and I
wanted to tell every parent, you know
what, if
your child is struggling in school, you
need to take them to a developmental
optometrist, not a regular optometrist.
Right.
Okay, it's
Those guys tell you everything's fine your
whole life. That's what happened for me.
That's what happened to my daughter. I
specifically asked my optimetrist if she
had
a problem with depth perception. And he
told me she was fine. So you can't even
get
this kind of a diagnosis at a regular
doctor's office. And they're not gonna
screen
for it in a school system, right? They're
only screening for acuity, you know, at
the eye chart across the room. There are
things they can do.
that are not that hard, but they're not
equipped all the time to do it. And what I
found when I said, you know, I really want
to tell this parent that they should take
their child to their per correct eye
doctor, the school system said, You can't
tell
them.
Why what? Why not?
Because the school doesn't want to have to
pay for vision therapy.
Yeah. Comes if it comes down to finances.
So they don't they don't they aren't even
questioning I'm drawing a parallel because
in terms of like in the non speaking world
the there are issues with schools not
allowing the use of letterboards or
communication partners in there. And
again, part
of it's financial, part of it in this case
is also
claims that, you know, it's not effective.
I mean they there's a lot of other
excuses they use in this. But I was
curious, so with this though, you think
it's
purely financial are do they don't even
they don't care if it's effective or not.
They just care about the cost.
Well, they're not trained to do it and
they're they don't have the funds to pay f
for, you know, a developmental optometrist
to do it.
But they can still recommend it, couldn't
they? I mean, couldn't they at least or
educate I don't see the harm in at least I
understand them saying, hey, we can't
provide this necessarily if this is an
additional cost, additional burden. I
mean, I
know financially, right? I mean, our we
ask a lot of our schools and s and stuff,
and that's a another topic, but I can at
least understand that from a financial
standpoint, if that's just an additional
cost to burden. But to at least say, hey,
here's something you should look at.
I think it's a big problem. Yeah. That's
why I'm saying I had to just not be in
education. You know? And that kind of
pointed me towards what I ended up doing,
right? At the end of the day, that's why
I'm doing podcasting because we need
awareness.
So that really what that really did just
kinda cause you were teaching, right? You
were substantial.
I was substituting yeah I it
Yeah, no, in the meantime I had to find
something that was gonna pay the bills.
Right. So instead of going the route of
alternative l route to licensure and
getting
a teaching certificate and being in the
school system, I got my insurance license.
I
sold insurance for ten years. Finished
raising my children and all of that. And
in
the meantime, you know, that gave me
flexibility to focus on my own healing, to
do
my vision therapy, to get my child in.
And you know, get all of that handled, get
them all married off. And then that's
good. then I was able to spend more time
on my podcast.
Ha
And how and remind me how long you've been
doing your podcast?
I started it in twenty about the time.
Wow, good for you. Wow. That's amazing.
Yeah, well, and I started it before I had
everybody out of the house and there were
some downtimes. You know, I think every
podcaster gets to the point where they're
questioning whether they're able to
continue, right? And my point in time
happened
when I had three daughters get married in
the space of four months in the summer of
twenty one. I blame that on COVID.
COVID marriages.
Well, they were all dating from the dating
apps and stuff, you know? And they all
Yeah, plan that a little bit, spread it
out a little bit for your sake? I mean,
geez, that's a lot.
You would think. Yeah. So that happened
and I had my third daughter get married by
September of that year. And then the f and
I had one podcast come out that year, you
know, in that summer. Yeah. And then I had
some technical issues and I just let life
get to me, you know, the whole now I'm an
empty nester, what's my life look like?
And then in April of twenty two my I
actually lost my husband in a motorcycle
accident. Oh
And so that kind of shut me down as a
podcaster too, you know. So people look at
my
dates on my podcast, there's this huge gap
in there, you know. Oh I finally had to
just say, you know what, this is why I'm
still here, part of why I'm still here,
you
know, is because I still have work to do.
I mean, there's a reason why he had to go
and I had to stay, you know. So I got back
into it.
Well understandably.
What are some of the lessons you've
learned? I'm curious from podcasting,
first of
all, and some of the guests that you've
had on there. What have what are or what
are
a couple of maybe surprising things that
have come from it, that journey?
Surprising is a good question. I started
to see how the whole body fits into the
picture. If we look at it just from the
eye standpoint, we limit ourselves, you
know? And if we look at it from a whole
body perspective, then we can say, okay,
what is the real cause of this problem? Is
there an alignment problem in the body
that we can look at?
Yes.
that will help us along the way or that is
signaling that there's something going on
with the eyes even. I for this is a great
example of my from my own life. I was born
pigeon toed. So we already have a
misalignment, right? The way they handled
that
back in my day, since I'm so old, is that
they would put casts on your on the baby's
feet.
I remember hearing about that.
for like six weeks. And then after the
cast comes off, then they put a bar with
two
with the orthopedic shoes, right? And the
shoes are pointing out and you have to
wear that and most of the time, you know.
I remember it being during naps and stuff,
you know. Like it was it was a thing that
well, I had to do it with my oldest
daughter too. Like I my daughter had the
same problem. So I know.
So there's that misalignment that I think
you should pay attention to, you know,
because it the body's telling us
something, right? It's telling us that we
need to
pay attention to what's going on as far as
oh I take it I personally I take it back
to feelings too, but with my guests I have
talked with them about the fact that
there's misalignments in the body that we
could address as well.
So it's kind of a long answer. I don't
know if that gives you
It does. Yeah. No, I no, I'm just kinda
thinking as you're talking, about that.
You
know, the whole body approach. I th I
think it makes so much sense. And I think
it's
something that we've continued to learn
about, you know, as people in the medical
profession. It's kind of getting back to
what you said earlier. It's kind of funny.
You can we start w the topic was talking
about kind of the vision therapy and then
of course
You think about just the eyes, right? This
is just a you know has to and we and we
do that with our body, right? It's just
and in healthcare in general. Just one
thing. Oh, you have a problem with
headaches or whatever. So it's just, you
know,
it's a it's a headache problem. And you
know, where could we find out later it
could
be something related to a spine issue, you
know, a misalignment that's everything's
to your point.
Everything is so much more connected than
I think we're taught or realize or assume
or whatever. I'm you know, I'm again I'm
not sure. It's kind of like one of those
systemic things. And I'm sure I think some
of it's probably just kind of the you
know, traditional healthcare approach that
specialists in our age of specialists,
you kind of choose especially and so
right. I don't know. And they don't talk
right.
And they don't talk to each other. And in
our world today with vision even, the
ophthalmologists and the vision therapy
doctors don't typically talk to each other
either, which I think is malpractice,
honestly, because there's so much good
that
can be done when they collaborate. You
know, if I hadn't had vision therapy,
surgery, and more vision therapy, I would
not have gained three D vision.
Right.
But there's so few doctors that work
together. You know, and if you go in and
you
only have the surgery, the percentage of
success isn't even being measured. If you
want if you want the result to be three D
vision, they're only measuring whether the
eyes are aligned. So it th they consider
it a 'cause cosmetic surgery.
Right. That makes sense. Wow. Why don't
they talk more? Is it ego? Is it just is I
mean, is there is it is it a turf battle?
I mean, I honestly don't know. I mean
again we see this in other areas, right? I
mean I I'm drawing analogies to you know
the world I'm most familiar with in the
autism world, but in this world, what do
you
see, Denise?
I think it's an ego problem personally,
you know. I think they're so t caught up
in
where's the scientific proof, you know?
Well who's gonna do these studies that
prove
that you're gaining three D vision, you
know? It's
So that's is that kind of their
Yeah, that they'll say there's no studies
that prove it works. Well, there's all
kinds of people who can say, look, this
worked for me, you know, but everyone's
problem is so specific. Doing double blind
studies doesn't even work. I mean,
there's how would you even do a study like
that? You can't find people whose
situation is exactly the same, no one's
is. So you can't do a study on it.
How would we right.
That is so interesting. and again, that I
was just gonna say, Denise, that's the
connection. That's exact because that's
exactly the battle that parents and you
know
non speakers are fighting as well in our
world. And when talking about the world of
letterboards and you know, we call it
spelling to communicate and all this, the
establishment, in this case the speech and
hearing association, therapist
association.
They use the exact same argument. There's
no s you know, this isn't scientific.
There's no scientific proof. And the
response is, you know, the proof is in
what
you're seeing. I mean, people are using it
successfully. And it sounds very similar
to what you're saying with vision therapy.
So it sounds like kind of traditional I
eye doctors see vision therapy as I don't
know, is do they see it as like woo-woo
sort or kind of
Yeah, I think they do. there's so many
times that they just say, Oh, it doesn't
work, or you're not a candidate, or they
don't even mention it to someone who's
been
in for vis for eye surgery. They'll say,
Well, this surgery might not work, you
might need another one. I mean, I'm on
these support groups for Strubismus on
Facebook and it's a constant thing.
Wow.
They just they don't tell him about it.
Yeah, that's like I said, that's that
blows me away in a way, again the
parallels
that we see. And you don't you don't know
what you don't know. So going back 'cause
you know, one of the c obvious questions
would be, Denise, is for parents, what
should they be looking for? I mean, if
your if your eye doctor's not gonna give
you
a heads up, like, hey, here's you know,
here's something to look for, if they're
not
gonna steer you to vision therapy or you
know, some of these other you know
Treatments? What should the parents be
looking for?
Well, I kind of alluded to it a little bit
with what I mentioned about my daughter's
story. You know, th asking those specific
questions if your child is verbal and can
tell you, right? Obviously it's way harder
if your child's not verbal and they can't
tell you, but I have a little checklist
that I made for parents. Again, it's gonna
it's gonna be a little harder depending on
your child. But if they're
But no, it's is it on your website or do
you do you have that I want to hear it?
Yeah, and I can go I can go over the short
list. It's a very yeah, so they lose
place or skip lines or reread something
and when they're reading. they avoid
reading
or they get frustrated really quickly.
they would understand better when they're
listening than when they're reading. They
have a short attention span for
schoolwork, but if they have a preferred
activity, their attention span is long.
they get tired or emotional or overwhelmed
during learning tasks.
Right.
They're clumsy like I was. They bump into
things or they struggle with coordination.
anytime you've been told everything is
fine and you still have concerns, that's
the
time to go and have it checked out, you
know. But the thing is that a regular
optometrist or an ophthalmologist is not
gonna look for the same kinds of things as
a developmental optometrist will look for.
Right.
So you really have to go to the right
doctor.
That makes a lot of sense now. And this is
kind of this may be kind of a dumb
question, but can if your child has, you
know, this type of vision and w I mean,
would they still be able to appear normal,
yeah, but they have normal vision in
other ways, like playing video games or
things like that. Is that affected?
Yeah, I mean a video game isn't gonna have
a depth perception requirement.
So that's easy that's easier 'cause it's
not okay.
Yeah. I mean it's in two D most of the
time, you know, unless you're playing with
the VR headset. Which actually a lot of
vision therapy doctors are starting to use
the VR.
I was wondering about that, if that would
be helpful with that.
Yeah, I actually even have one and I I've
been so anti-video games that I can't make
myself do it, but I bought one and I was
like, I'm gonna do this. And I haven't.
But
it is something that a lot of patients
find very helpful.
Yeah, no, you've just you've got me
thinking in terms of and I'm just
thinking, are
there are there any other questions that
you can ask your child again that maybe
aren't reading related or things I'm
thinking about again, our audience who
maybe
have non-speakers but can communicate
through typing. are there any other side
things that they can ask or ways to try to
determine if this is a problem or a
potential problem or issue?
This things I'm seeing in on these
checklists are gonna have to do with being
able
to keep your place, you know. So the hand
eye coordination piece could apply to
nonverbal, you know, if they if they have
a hard time even picking something up or
catching or whatever, right? That's a high
hand eye coordination issue. I remember
Gillian saying that she used to stick out
her pinky when she was grabbing the cup.
You know, because it helped her orient
where her hand was gonna go. oh You would
see
compensations in that hand eye
coordination piece.
Where her hand was, yeah.
Okay.
Great. Well, let's move on to our weekly
segments because I know that you are
prepared. Thank you, Denise, for coming
prepared. yeah. And so we're gonna start
off
and for each of these, just give you fair
warning, we do have little jingles that
will that Dave, producer Dave will play
and then we'll get we'll start off with
the
tip of the week. It won't necessarily be
autism tip of the week, but it'll be
Denise's tip of the week.
Hey parents, gather round, it's time to
speak We're here with your tip of the week
Strategies and wisdom just for you Autism
parents, we know what you go through
All right, it's time for our tip of the
week. And as I mentioned earlier, I know
that Denise, you brought one for us. What
do you have?
Well, we've kind of talked about it a
little bit already, but just pointing to
the
fact that a child may be able to see
clearly and still have difficulty using
their
two eyes together, and a regular vision
screening, even at a doctor's office, may
not tell the whole story.
Okay, that's a great that's a great tip.
and I was gonna ask kind of a related tip,
if every parent could know one thing about
binocular vision, what would it be?
Well, not everyone has it. Okay. You know.
Yeah. It I think we just take that for
granted. not just as a parent, but as a as
a person alive on the earth today, we
just think everyone sees like we do.
Yeah, right. You just assume that.
I've talked to so many people they don't
even know what binocular vision means.
They
and I there I say, Well, I didn't see in
three D before and they say, Well, do I
see
in three D? I said, Well, probably. I
don't know. I can't see like you do.
I don't think.
Yeah, that's funny. All right. Next up we
have factor fiction. Time ready, and here
we go. This is autism factor fiction.
We're breaking down what's real, what's
rumored, and what might surprise you.
Let's go. All right. So this is again
where I
like to introduce potential stereotypes or
myths or, you know, things that may
misperspe misperceptions that may be out
there. But
oh
Denise, what do you have for fact or
fiction?
Well, again, we've talked about a lot of
this, so I'm kind of feeling like maybe
this is just a review. the fact or fiction
that I chose was twenty means that your
vision is fine.
Right. I think that's a big one though. I
think that bears repeating because I think
that's such a that it that I think that's
just presumed to be fact. I think that's
just so ingrained in us that that's the
goal. It's just all about twenty vision
that
you don't even don't even think about
that.
Right. And because my gl my glasses
corrected my vision so that it was twenty
I must
be fine. Right.
Yeah. And I guess kind of related to that
would be, you know, I'd jotted down, you
know, like my child passed their vision
screening, you know, at school. So I'm
everything's fine. That yeah. That true.
And being told that you're fine for years
and years and years. And knowing that
you're not really.
I mean there's a little bit of trauma that
goes with that, right? I mean kinda isn't
it a little bit of being like gaslit for
so many years? Like you're like, I know
this isn't true, but I can't prove it.
Yes, and I've heard it from many of my
guests as well.
That they knew that they knew something
was wrong, but
Yeah, and one in particular had the
strabismus surgery and went back to her
surgeon
and said, You know, I'm really struggling.
She had a complete breakdown of her
visual system after her surgery. You know,
you move the eyes around, she's used to
compensating a certain way. And her eyes
had no idea what to do at that point. And
this was a while after the surgery that
she had this complete breakdown. And they
treated her like she was crazy, like she
should just
But they literally said, it's all in your
head.
Unbelievable.
It was all into her head because it was
her brain not knowing how to tell her how
to
work together. Right.
Right, No, I go back to li the point you
made w right off the bat, Denise, in terms
of how our eyes are muscles and if you're
gonna have surgery on a muscle, it's just
like anything else. Like I can't imagine
someone who goes through, say, you know,
again, sports related that people relate,
you know, can go through ACL surgery and
just like you just have surgery and then
say, Okay, you're good to go.
Without PT, right? Without any type of
follow up. I mean, it sounds like that's
kind
of the expectation with eye the eye
surgery.
It is. Yeah. And that's actually one of my
favorite analogies. You would never have
surgery on any other part of your body and
not have physical therapy surgery or
after surgery or both. Right. And yet
that's what we are doing all the time with
vision with our eyes with our eye surgery.
Yeah.
That's crazy. Sorry. That's that really is
crazy. I mean, that's just I guess it
just seems yeah. It seems like there's we
need to progress the view there. Like in
as we have in so many other areas of
medicine and healthcare. I'll put it that
way.
Saying it's just crazy isn't very
productive.
Well, it's not but the a awareness is what
we're trying to do so that people will
know that there needs to be a ship. You
know, it we ha we have to demand it of the
doctors.
Right. Yeah. And that's yeah, and that
that's kind of like a whole nother
conversation, right, Denise, is changing
our mindset. as patients in general, as
advocates for our kids, you know, dealing
with doctors. trusting them as experts,
which they are, they're trained, they're,
you know, they have a lot of education and
training, which deserves respect. But that
doesn't mean they're all known.
all knowing and they and they don't know
our bodies. I mean they can't at best a
lot
of what they're doing is still kind of
making educated guesses about the
approach,
which, you know, that's just the way it
works. But
And it's true in the vision therapy room
too. They have to figure out where the
missing piece is, you know. And you can
talk about vision therapy with relation to
traumatic brain injury and everything too.
And, you know, I've had many of my guests
that work with that.
population say if you've treated one
person with a traumatic brain injury,
you've
treated one person with a traumatic brain
injury, you know. So there's just a lot of
things going on with that, you know, and I
think some of the autistic population
falls into that traumatic brain injury
category too, right? And so it's just
they're
practicing medicine, you know, they're
trying to figure it out.
Yeah.
Yeah, for sure. No, I mean it's
fascinating. All right. Well, next up on
our segment
is gonna be our confession of the week,
parent confession.
Teens can go astray, found socks in the
fridge one day. Laughter's the best
remedy,
hey, we're just finding our own way.
Sharing joys and moments we seek, honest
tales that make us unique. Join the crowd,
we're never meek.
All right, now's the time when we get to,
as I always say, share our humanity so
that we don't have just have the answers.
We've made mistakes too. And Denise, I
mean, with six kids, I'm sure there's a
couple of things that may have come to
mind.
But what, yeah, what would you like to
share with everyone?
Well, you know, we I already talked about
my daughter Abby and how I didn't know
that she needed vision therapy till I
knew, right? I don't talk about this a
lot,
but I actually had a another child who had
some struggles and still does actually.
there's another vision issue called
convergence insufficiency. And
My son had been struggling in school. We
thought that he was just lazy because he
could read, he could do the work. If he
did the work, he got a hundred percent, he
got an A. If most of the time he didn't do
the work, most of the time. And it was
not until he was 15 that we had him
diagnosed.
Okay.
And my doctor said it was probably the
worst case of convergence insufficiency
he'd
ever seen.
What is it? Can you give it a
Convergence insufficiency means that when
you try to focus close, your eyes just
give up. You can only sustain the
convergence, the eyes working together
close up
for a limited amount of time before it's
just too tiring and it it's
It's like a overload probably, right?
And you just don't want to do it, right?
Which is so why he wouldn't focus on his
work, you know. Just didn't want to do it
because it was so hard to do it. And I did
I took him to vision therapy. He did
several months of vision therapy, and he
was
just not really progressing with it, you
know. Okay. Yeah. And so, you know, by
that
age, it's really hard to force them to do
it.
Okay.
Sure.
And I gave up. That's my big convention
actually. I don't I hardly ever talk about
it.
Yeah.
And it's still I mean, he doesn't if he
wants to do something he figures out how
to
do it. He's very smart. He can do whatever
he wants to. But it schoolwork is not it.
He's yeah, he it sounds like he's found
other ways of coping and other ways to get
things done. But he also knows that
option's there, right?
He does. Yeah. And I've told him that many
times. You know, you can go back and do
the vision therapy and get the results if
you want to.
Yeah. Well that I can see where that would
be really difficult. But there's only so
much that you can do too, right? I mean,
that's the part that I think we all
struggle with as parents is we you know,
we want to be able to control as much as
we
can. We want to be able to boost our kids
and help them. And I was just having that
conversation with my brother the other
day. It's a it's a really tough balancing
act
between like is it pushing too hard or you
know.
and pulling back too far too. And I the
unfortunately there's no there's no
perfect
answer, right? You just do what you just
do what you think is best. But yeah, thank
you. Thank you for sharing that. That's I
mean I really appreciate that. Well we're
gonna turn it around 180 and again because
we like to end this on a lighter note. So
we have our semi news segment which is
light on the spectrum.
Yeah.
Light on the spectrum, oh a moment, person
or story bring in something good. It
feels hopeful, grounded, not performative.
Use it for a person, a moment, a
breakthrough, a story.
All right, so like I said, what do you
have for us, Denise, to give our
listeners,
parents out there, a little bit of hope?
Well, I think that the my story is my
biggest gift, right? Because
neuroplasticity
is a real thing, you know. You don't have
to say, Oh, this is just the way it is.
And I mean I've heard it so many times.
People will say, I have permanent double
vision. I will never see in 3D. Happens
all the time, you know. And
When I went into my surgeon for my first
visit with him and I told him that my goal
was to see in 3D, he didn't take that
super well, really. You know, he actually
told
me that he wanted me to come back in and
do some more testing because they were
getting some new machine in there that was
gonna be able to gauge whether I'd be
successful, that kind of thing. And I
already knew I was gonna be successful.
But
He didn't, you know, and so I waited and I
went back in and I did their all their s
testing and stuff and found out that he
actually and I'm it probably shouldn't
share, but I knew he knew that he thought
that I was being unrealistic.
Right, sure. He's being he's being overly
cautious or overly skeptical or you know
choose your choose your word, right? I
mean.
Right. But I mean neuroplasticity says our
brains can change, right? The way we see
can change, the way we do things can
change, we our bodies can improve in many
different ways, right? We see that all the
time at every age. But yeah. Doesn't
matter if you're fifty or seventy or
twenty, right? It can change. And so my
We're out of
gift is that I proven it can change. You
know, I gained three D vision at age fifty
four.
That's amazing. Yeah, that's a great
message. That should give a lot of people
hope.
And like you said, especially the message
about neuroplasticity and just how it
can't be emphasized enough because again
there's so many contexts where we hear
that. like you said, I have permanent XYZ.
for those of us like in an autism world,
you know, we've dealt with a lot of
negativity and we've and now we're seeing
a lot
of positives.
So before we wrap up, Denise, how can
people find you?
Well, I have my podcast on every podcast
player. And recently I put it on YouTube.
It's got a static image. I don't do video
because I'm not that but well I just
haven't felt like I could edit a video.
I'm good at editing audio. So it but it is
on YouTube, it's on all the podcast
players, Healing Our Site. I have a
Facebook
group also called Healing Our Site.
Okay.
And website. Healing our site. Awesome.
Yeah. So they can reach me in any of those
ways.
Great. Well thank you, Denise, for joining
us today. I really enjoyed the
conversation. I know that our listeners
and viewers will walk away looking at a
vision.
And eyes, maybe even the brain, a little
differently. And thanks to all of you for
spending part of your day with us. If you
enjoyed today's episode, please subscribe,
leave us a review, share it with someone
you think would benefit from the
conversation. This is one of the best ways
to help us reach more families. Continue
bringing these important stories to a
wider audience. I'd also like to give a
special thank you.
To our producer, my guy, Dave Yaz, and the
entire team at Pod 617. Dave's been with
me since the beginning of our podcast.
We're coming up on two years. His
expertise,
creativity, and friendship have helped
make the lighter side of the spectrum what
it
is today. So again, thank you, Denise, and
we'll catch everyone else next week.